Guide to the Records of the A/P/A Voices A COVID-19 Public Memory Project TAM.837
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Hoa, Vincent, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_30
  In the second part of the interview Hoa discusses the Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests in New York City and nationally. He describes feeling moved by the protests, as a person of color, and applauded the protests for both having widespread support and remaining centered around the particular experiences of Black people. Hoa talks about how the protests opened up conversations in his personal life and among coworkers; and how he connects the protests with the backdrop of inequalities produced by the pandemic lockdown. Hoa talks about the feeling of seeing Confederate statues torn down in his hometown of Richmond, Virginia and connects local police abolitionist movements with an international analysis of imperialism. Hoa also discusses paying rent during the pandemic and rent strikes in New York City. The interview concludes with Hoa discussing changes in their emotional experiences of the pandemic, from early despair to renewed hope because of the protests.
  "Vincent Hoa" (pseudonym) was born and raised in Richmond, VA and has lived in New York City since 2015. His parents are refugees from Vietnam. Hoa is a gardener with the New York City Parks Department and works in the borough of Brooklyn. Hoa was asked to participate in the A/P/A Voices project because of his experience as an essential worker and city employee during the COVID-19 lockdown in New York City.
- Huynh, Hoai-An Melody, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_31
  Materials include Huynh's drawing, "Mani-curing the Hate," and an explanation of the piece.
- Jason, 2020
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_33
    Materials include video files from an oral history interview conducted by Vivian Truong on August 11, 2020. In his interview, Jason discusses working in the Emergency Department at a hospital in Houston, TX in March 2020 when COVID-19 cases began to rise in the United States; and the lack of proper precautions and personal protective equipment (PPE) for healthcare workers, especially in the early months of the pandemic. Jason reflects on the confusion between varying COVID-19 protocols in the different hospitals where he worked and the need for nurses to advocate for their own health as well as their patients'.
    Jason traveled to work in New York City for twelve weeks from April to July 2020, as cases began to plateau following the height of the first wave. He lived in Chinatown while working in New York City and describes how the neighborhood had come to a standstill before slowly reopening during the summer. After New York City, Jason traveled to another assignment in Albuquerque, NM. He describes his experience traveling during the pandemic and encountering people who did not believe in the severity of the pandemic. The interview ends with Jason's concerns that the full effects of the pandemic have not yet been realized and his hopes for lessons learned for the future.
    Jason is a traveling nurse and a former community organizer. He was born in New York and raised in South Florida. Jason was working in the Emergency Department at a hospital in Houston, TX in March 2020 when COVID-19 cases began to rise in the United States.
- Jennifer, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_34
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Ronak Gandhi on February 25, 2021. During the interview, Jennifer talks about her experience during the pandemic, her family background, and her parents' undocumented status. Jennifer expresses a great sense of urgency and suppresses anger about the treatment her parents face; and the "invisibility" of undocumented workers, their workplace oppression, and their troubled relationship with the government. Jennifer describes how completing unemployment paperwork for her family occupied a large space in her mind, particularly since her parents could not fill it out themselves as they do not speak English. The interview also discusses Jennifer's life as a student during three distinct phases: the spring semester post-COVID-19, the summer, and the fall return to campus.
  Jennifer is from Queens, NY and grew up in a predominantly Black, Indigenous, and People of Color (BIPOC) working class neighborhood. She studied sociology at Yale University with a focus on ethnicity, race, and migration.
- Jeung, Russell, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_35
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Diane Wong on December 18, 2020. The interview began with Russell Jeung talking about being in the Bay Area and contextualizing the present moment within longer Asian American histories. Jeung talks about his involvement as one of the founders of Stop Asian American Pacific Islander (AAPI) Hate, a web-based project that logs occurrences of hate crimes against Asian Americans. Jeung talks about both new and old resistance tactics including the use of social media to combat misinformation and bullying in schools. Over the summer, he worked with a group of over a hundred youths from across the country on an anti-bullying school campaign that involved the leveraging of social media and outreach to well-known YouTubers and international celebrities like Jeremy Lin.
  Jeung also discusses the involvement of South Asian youths and organizers in combating anti-Asian hate in the wake of COVID-19. The group applied strategies and knowledge gained post-9/11, in an attempt to support documenting anti-Asian hate in the present moment. Jeung also discusses how disproportionately Asian Americans have been impacted by the pandemic in other ways from access to health care, language assistance, and small business closures. The interview ends with Jeung sharing his vision for a justice-oriented vision for the future where Asian Americans are working closely with other communities of color specifically around issues of restorative justice and transformation.
  Russell Jeung is a co-founder of Stop Asian American Pacific Islander (AAPI) Hate, a web-based project that logs occurrences of hate crimes against Asian Americans. The project was born out of a need to document hate-crimes directed towards Asian Americans and to challenge the false narrative President Trump had been advocating that Chinese Americans are the reason for the pandemic. As of December 2020, the project has since documented over 3,000 incidents of anti-Asian hate with Asian American women being disproportionately impacted. The project made national and local policy impacts by pushing for accountability through legislation, but also structural changes that address the roots of racism.
- Keo, Mike, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_36
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on October 20, 2020. In his interview, Mike Keo talks extensively about the rise of anti-Asian racism during the COVID-19 lockdown; references the historical roots of discrimination against Asians; shares his personal experiences with discrimination; and the impact of the virus on his career and family. Keo discusses the online platform he has created, along with his team of volunteers and educators, to address the problems of anti-Asian racism through a media campaign; films and posters; a free downloadable Wellness Toolkit; educational materials for students that include a coloring book honoring Asian American community leaders; and a curriculum about Asian American history. Keo explains how by working on a local level, he has worked to 'stop hate' by partnering with schools and local leaders to develop projects that foster understanding and community building. The interview concludes with Keo discussing his #IAmNotAVirus online campaign, which was fueled by photographs he shot in his studio.
  Mike Keo is a Cambodian American wedding photographer and founder of the #IAmNotAVirus campaign, which was launched in response to the surge of Anti-Asian racism during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Khmer Girls in Action (KGA), 2020-2022
  Khmer Girls in Action is a Long Beach, CA-based youth organization acting in collaboration with the #WeCanDoThis campaign, a federal Department of Health and Human Services COVID-19 public education campaign.
  - Paper Files (Box Shared Tamiment 189, Folder 4-5)
    Materials include a set of original postcards, some of which include updated information on COVID-19 vaccines; a brochure about the organization; information about the #WeCanDoThis initiative as it relates to outreaching to Asian American, Pacific Islander, and Native Hawaiian (AAPINH) communities; and a few branded stickers.
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_37
    Materials include digital copies of the paper materials. There are also two videos produced to promote the #WeCanDoThis initiative, while also amplifying the perspectives of community members Keomoney Norn and Jocelyn Ly.
- Khurana, Sarita, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_38
  Sarita Khurana is a Brooklyn-based director, producer, and writer whose work focuses on South Asian stories and female subjectivities.
  Materials include Khurana's short film, Home, Delivered, which was commissioned by the Asian American Documentary Network as part of their COVID-19 storytelling series.
- Kim, Ha Kyung, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_39
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Mi Hyun Yoon on May 23, 2021. In her interview, Ha Kyung Kim talks about the lack of diversity where she lives, which has a 70 percent white population, and mentions that most of the Asian population in her community come from scientists and engineers who work for the military. Kim discusses her job, which she started in January 2020, and the impact the pandemic has had on it. Kim also mentions how her home gym has helped her through the pandemic and how, as a federal employee, she has not been able to actively participate in protests. For Asian American Pacific Islander Heritage month in 2021, Kim was recruited to be involved with program planning and she recounts how it was both a positive and negative experience.
  The transcript and video files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room only once permission has been obtained from Ha Kyung Kim.
  Ha Kyung Kim is a Korean American woman who lives in Bel Air, MD and works as a HR specialist for the U.S. Army.
- Kim, Patricia, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_40
  Materials include the video "How to Start Talking to Your Korean Family about Black Lives Matter," which is in English with Korean subtitles.
- Kochiyama, Eddie, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_41
  Materials include Eddie Kochiyama's photographs of murals and graffiti in Oakland, CA; and Kochiyama's reflections on George Floyd's death.
- Kuo, Linda, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_42
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on April 29, 2021. In this interview Linda Kuo talks about the impact of the pandemic on her family and her dance company, Dancers Unlimited. As a Taiwanese born resident of Brooklyn, NY, she shares her thoughts about cultural appropriation and the role of traditional dance in Pacific Islander communities; her observations of anti-Asian racism in Hawai'i; and the ways she has coped with the isolation and mental health issues she experienced during this past year under lock-down. In the interview, Kuo shares an open rehearsal of her new project, Edible Tales, a dance about Taro, a food staple in the Pacific Islands. Taro is presented as symbol of the resilience of Indigenous people. At the end of the interview, Linda speaks about shifting towards healing.
  Linda Kuo is a co-founder, director, and choreographer of Dancers Unlimited (DU), a bicoastal dance company based in New York City and Hawai'i. Born in Taiwan and raised in Hawai'i, Kuo is shaped by cultural diversity and performing arts including dancing the Hula. As a choreographer, Kuo's work has been presented on stages in New York City, Hawai'i, and abroad. Kuo's Hawaiian upbringing is influential in her artistry and creative approach. Dancing the Hula helped cement her belief in dance as the backbone of cultural identity and resilience. Her choreography addresses social and cultural issues, while fusing contemporary, street, and cultural dances with a strong emphasis on authentic and diverse storytelling; and her creative vision emphasizes community engagement as part of her mission. Kuo has trained in the BOLD (Builders, Organizer, and Leaders through Dance) program by the Urban Bush Women and studied at its Summer Leadership Institute at New York University. She also volunteered to conduct interviews for the A/P/A Voices project.
- Labor Notes, 2020-2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_43
  Materials include an interview with Annie Tan about growing anti-Asian racism with the emergence of the COVID-19 pandemic and an article by Saurav Sarkar about the same topic.
- Lam, Kevin, 2020-2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_44
  Materials include transcript, audio files, and video files from two oral history interviews conducted by Vivian Truong on July 24, 2020 and March 1, 2021. In the July 24, 2020 interview, Kevin Lam discusses his personal experience of the pandemic, the Asian American Resource Workshop's (AARW) responses to the multiple crises facing its membership base, and the organization's shift to remote work during the early days of the pandemic. Whereas AARW primarily focused on community organizing in the years leading up to the outbreak of COVID-19, responding to the pandemic meant an increased focus on direct service, including raising funds for impacted community members and coordinating grocery deliveries. The organization also had to shift its ongoing campaigns on gentrification, deportation, and policing to address the domino-like effects of the pandemic on each of these issue areas.
  Lam expresses his concern for his parents, who are essential workers in the manufacturing industry, and among the few Asian families in their area during a time of rising anti-Asian sentiment. As refugees of the Vietnam War, Lam's parents approached both the public health threat of the pandemic and the potential for anti-Asian violence as yet another period of crisis through which to survive. As a form of personally coping with the isolation of stay-at-home directives, Lam nourished his connection to his Vietnamese and Laotian identity through cooking. Lam discusses how Black Lives Matter (BLM) reinforced the necessity of intergenerationally engaging Asian immigrant members in solidarity work with Black communities, particularly in relation to defunding the police and decarceration. The interview ends with Kevin's reflection on the sustainability of movement-building through and beyond the era of COVID-19.
  In the March 1, 2021 interview, Lam discusses a deportation case AARW worked on prior to the pandemic involving a Cambodian American. Lam shares how anti-deportation organizers are approaching the immigration policies of the new presidential administration and explains how AARW continues to coordinate mutual aid efforts, including culturally relevant grocery deliveries to Asian immigrant communities in Boston. While the organization did not consider direct service provision to be a main part of their work prior to COVID-19, the pandemic helped change AARW's understanding of the relationship between direct service and community organizing. The interview also includes reflections after a year of the pandemic where Lam shares the need for healing and mental health care to address the traumatic effects of the pandemic that would persist after its "end."
  Kevin Lam grew up in Poughkeepsie, NY and his parents are Laotian and Vietnamese refugees. As of 2020, he was the Organizing Director of the Asian American Resource Workshop (AARW), founded in 1979. AARW works with Asian and Asian American communities in the greater Boston area, including Vietnamese residents of the neighborhood of Dorchester. The organization focuses their community organizing on issues including gentrification, deportation, and policing.
- Latif, Khalid, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_45
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Zaim Alam on April 13, 2021. In this interview, Khalid Latif talks about his efforts early in the pandemic to immediately fundraise and guide resources to students, first responders, and community members -- often in multi-family households in the outskirts of the boroughs -- who were unable to leave the city or shelter-in-place. He spoke in great detail about his experience living in Lower Manhattan, on New York University's campus, and feeling empowered by how much his local community in New York and in the Muslim community at large stepped up to serve, however they could, during this crisis.
  Towards the end of the interview, Latif recounts a moving story about his children, who he says in many ways taught him more than he taught them. In Muslim tradition, children are often taught how to make "dua," or supplications to God at the end of their prayers, often asking God for health, guidance, protection. As ambulances became the soundtrack of New York City in the worst days of the pandemic, Latif's son would lead his younger sibling in prayer oriented toward the ambulances, asking God to protect and have mercy on everyone inside. When the George Floyd protests erupted, Latif's son did the same, praying for the protestors and everyone else involved in the streets below.
  Khalid Latif is the Executive Director and Imam for the Islamic Center at New York University. In 2005, Latif was appointed the first Muslim chaplain at NYU and in 2007, his position was fully institutionalized. While at NYU, Latif has initiated his vision for a pluralistic American Muslim community rooted on campus and reaching out to the city.
- Lee, Patrick, 2020
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_46
    Materials include audio files and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Minju Bae on July 24, 2020. In this interview, Patrick Lee talks about the COVID-19 pandemic, how it affected his filmmaking, what the pandemic's impacts were at queer clubs in Seoul, and how he understood what was unraveling in the U.S. from abroad.
    The audio files and video files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections or remotely. For remote access, a time sensitive online web link will be provided.
    Patrick Lee is a queer Korean American documentary filmmaker, writer, and organizer living in New York. At the beginning of the pandemic, he had been living in Seoul, Korea, working on a documentary film.
- Leong, Russell C., 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_47
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on August 5, 2020. Artwork, poetry, and photographs are also included that illustrate the emotional impact of sheltering in place during COVID-19.
  In his interview, Russell Leong connects his experiences with the SARS virus, for which he was quarantined while in Hong Kong in March 2003, to the COVID-19 pandemic. As a gay Asian man, he also reflects on the AIDS virus and his work volunteering for the A/P/A Intervention Team, working with Chinese immigrants who had AIDS. Leong talks about the ways class and race have contributed to the impact of the virus. He makes connections between the Black Lives Matter slogan of "I Can't Breathe" with the devastating and life-ending symptoms of COVID-19. He also speaks at length about racial justice movements and his Buddhist practice. Later in the interview, Leong shares a PowerPoint containing drawings he has donated to the A/P/A Voices Project and talks about the creative process behind this work. The interview concludes with Leong reading a poem he wrote about COVID-19.
  Russell Charles Leong is an academic editor, professor, writer, poet, practicing Buddhist, Asian American activist, and an artist. He was an editor of Amerasia Journal from 1977–2010; and an adjunct professor of English and Asian-American studies at University of California, Los Angeles. Leong serves as senior editor for international projects including the CUNY Forum, a quarterly journal published by the Asian American and Asian Research Institute (AARI) at the City University of New York.
- Liang, Kathy, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_48
  Materials include two drawings titled "You're not like FROM China" and "Community Work;" and explanations of these drawings.
- Liu, Chelsea and Dominique Xi, 2022; TW_TAM_837_ER_49
  Materials include a transcript, classroom presentation, and videos from an oral history interview conducted by Chelsea Liu on March 29, 2022 and April 23, 2022 with Dominque Xi on the subject of Asian American theatre arts activism during the COVID-19 pandemic. This oral history interview was not recorded as part of the A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project, but rather, was filmed as part of Liu's academic coursework.
  Chelsea Shi-Chao Liu is a graduate of Sarah Lawrence College and Claremont University's MA program in History & Archival Studies. She is an archivist and researcher with interests in Asian American studies; gender and sexuality; and visual culture.
  Dominique Xi is a graduate of Sarah Lawrence College and a multi-hyphenate filmmaker based in New York. Xi wrote and directed the short film, A Hero's Journey; executive produced the web series, STUCK; and acted in the Crossway's Theatre production of "COVID Crime."
- Ma, Jerry, circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_50
  Jerry Ma is a graphic artist and founder of the indie comics studio Epic Proportions. With Keith Chow, Parry Shen, and Jeff Yang, he is a co-author of Shattered: The Asian American Comics Anthology and a co-editor of Secret Identities: The Asian American Superhero Anthology, both published by The New Press.
  Materials include Jerry Ma's painting "I Am Asian American," which was a response to anti-Asian sentiments that had been growing during the pandemic. The painting highlights a variety of everyday people that were donating face shields, masks, food, time, and energy to the Asian American community. Those who work in the medical field are colored in blue, those who work in the food industry are colored red, and those who just wanted to help in their own unique way are colored in purple.
- Mauna Kea Protectors at the University of Hawai'i, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_51
  Materials include a letter dated June 14, 2020 from the Mauna Kea Protectors at the University of Hawai'i to the university administration, renewing its support for the Kia'i who are defending Mauna Kea from Thirty-Meter Telescope development -- just one month short of the one-year anniversary of sustained community resistance to the ongoing desecration on Mauna Kea. This support continued amidst the COVID-19 shelter in place orders and the demonstrations for the Black, Indigenous, and People of Color (BIPOC) community.
- Mock, Emily, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_52
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on August 28, 2020. Photographs of Emily Mock and her work with CAAAV: Organizing Asian Communities are also included.